<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Our demands of the English lords manifested, being at Rippon Octob. 8. 1640 With answers to the complaints and grievances given in by the Bishop of Durham, Northumberland, and some of Nevvcastle; said to be committed by our Army.</title>
            <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11673</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21926</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116862</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852077</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852077</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17380</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11673)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17380)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1495:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Our demands of the English lords manifested, being at Rippon Octob. 8. 1640 With answers to the complaints and grievances given in by the Bishop of Durham, Northumberland, and some of Nevvcastle; said to be committed by our Army.</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Army.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, by Margery Mar-Prelat [i.e. the Cloppenburg Press],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The imprint is false; printed in Amsterdam at the Cloppenburg Press (STC).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Durham (England : County) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Northumberland (England) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17380:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17380:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>OVR DEMANDS OF THE ENGLISH LORDS MANIFESTED, BEING AT RIPPON <hi>Octob.</hi> 8. 1640.</p>
            <p>WITH ANSWERS TO THE COMPLAINTS AND GRIEVANCES GIVEN IN BY THE BISHOP OF DUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HAM, NORTHUMBERLAND, and ſome of NEVVCASTLE; ſaid to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by our Army.</p>
            <p>Printed, by MARGERY MAR-PRELAT. 1640.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="statement_of_English_lords_demands">
            <pb facs="tcp:17380:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17380:2"/>
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <head>I R</head>
                  <figDesc>decorative illustration consisting of a central Tudor rose surmounted by a crown with the Tudor rose and English lion on one side and the Scottish thistle and unicorn on the other</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>At <hi>RIPPON</hi> 
                  <date>the 8. of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1640.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OTHING is more heartily wiſhed of us, and of thoſe that ſent us, then that the Treaty may begin tymouſly, and end <hi>happily.</hi> This mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us in our laſt <hi>Propoſition</hi> to deſire to know what your Lordſhips did conceive to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petencie for the maintenance of our Army; and now after his Majeſty is acquainted therewith, we deſire to know his Majeſties mind, that the Army being provided for in a competent manner; and ſo much being made known to ſuch as ſent us, according to the inſtructions which we have received from them, which make the maintenance of the Army grievous to the Treaty; we may with all diligence ſhew them his Majeſties pleaſure concerning the change of the place, and new power to be granted for concluding: And as we are wa ranted to give this anſwer, ſo will we not conceale our own thoughts about all this matter of the maintenance of the Army, transferring of the Treaty to <hi>Yorke,</hi> and enlarging of our power. Firſt, it is univerſally known that our Army was ſtayed in the March by his Majeſties ſpeciall command, without which they might before this time, either have been better provided, or further advanced in their <hi>Petitions</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions;</hi> and that in hope of proviſion to be made this way, they have kept up from taking ſuch wayes, and uſing ſuch meanes, as may ſerve for their neceſſary maintenance, which yet are not to lay any burden upon the Nation or good People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whoſe <hi>weale</hi> and <hi>happineſſe</hi> we ſeek as our own; and with whom we have determined as we have declared, to ſtand or to fall. But our meaning is, that our neceſſary maintenance being denyed to the Army, we take our ſelves to thoſe Papiſts and Prelats, with their adherents, our profeſt enemies, and the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy inſtruments of all our troubles, and charges and hazards theſe yeares by paſt, who therefore ought in all equity to ſuffer in the ſame kind.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:17380:3"/>
            <p>Next we cannot conceive what danger may be apprehended in our going to <hi>Yorke,</hi> and caſting our ſelves and others who may be joyned with us into the hands of an Army, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Lievtenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> againſt whom as a chiefe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendiary (according to our Demands, which are the ſubject of the Treaty it ſelfe) we intend to inſiſt; as is expreſt, in our <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance</hi> and <hi>Declaration,</hi> who hath in the Parliament of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> proceeded againſt us as Traytors, and Rebbels, the beſt Title it pleaſed his Lordſhip in his common Table to honour us with, whoſe Commiſſion is to ſubdue and deſtroy us; and who by all meanes profeſſeth the breaking up of all Treaties of peace, as fearing to be excluded in the end; command alſo by diverſe Papiſts, who conceive our <hi>Pacification</hi> to be their <hi>ruine</hi> and <hi>deſolation;</hi> and where there are divers others our god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and diſnaturall Countrey-men, doing the moſt offices about his Majeſty, and waiting the occaſion of expreſſing their malice and revenge againſt us and their own Nation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the whole Committie cannot be tranſmitted to us and them, nor the want of neither hath been, nor needeth it to be any hinderance of the ſpeedy progreſſe and peaceable concluſion of the Treaty, ſince we have already in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our <hi>Conference</hi> ſhewed to your Lordſhips what is the ſubject and ſubſtance of our demands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_bishops_replies_to_demands">
            <pb facs="tcp:17380:3"/>
            <head>ANSWERS TO THE COMPLAINTS AND GRIEVANCES GIVEN IN BY THE BISHOP OF DURHAM, NORTHUMBRLAND, and ſome of NEVV-CASTLE; ſaid to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by our Army.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E did crave in the Treaty that before Anſwere was given to them, that either the ſuppliants, or ſome repreſenting them, may put their hands to the ſupplications and grievances, to the effect, that if they have Calumniated our Army, they may have <hi>Lex talionis.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The neceſſity of our ſtay at <hi>New-caſtle,</hi> with our Army, till we ſent ſupplications to his Majeſty, which was returned with a referrnce to the 24. <hi>Septemb.</hi> and a commandement to come no further into <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. We ſent to the Iuſtices of Peace to meet with us, that our regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler way might be layed and proſecuted, for the entertainment of our Army with leſse trouble to the Countrey, whereof ſome came, and ſome refuſed; thoſe of the Biſhopricke offered to lend us 350. pound <hi>per diem;</hi> thoſe of <hi>Northumberland</hi> 300. pound <hi>per diem,</hi> the way of ſettling it being unknown to us, we conceived it a voluntary way of friendly borrowing. The projects of this rayſed almoſt as much more of the County; whereupon ſo many complaints came to us, that we tooke another courſe to prevent the abuſe of our ſelves and the Countrey.</item>
               <item>4. The offer of <hi>New-caſtle</hi> was voluntary, and a contract for borrowed money: If we had bin ſuch as we are deſcribed, we might
<pb facs="tcp:17380:4"/> have uſed ſome rygour, which we have not done, ſeeing they have neither kept word, nor writt with us.</item>
               <item>5. In all our demands we meant nothing but borrowing from Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and to repay it: but from Papiſts and Prelats prize, they hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been our adverſaries, and borne Armes againſt us.</item>
               <item>6. We have not 6. pence from any without order, but upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint the offenders being known, they have had redreſſe to the full, and the offenders punished.</item>
               <item>7. For the Complaints of the Bishops, Deanes, Prebends, Parſons, they rifled their own houſes themſelves, left their doores open, and fled from them: ſo that if there were juſtice in the Land, they may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed before the Chief Iuſtice, for the pillageing their own houſes, and accuſing others.</item>
               <item>8. If any ſtragling Souldiers committed any pillageing, we doe not allow it, but knowing it shall punish it.</item>
               <item>9. All Robberyes committed cannot be imputed to our Army, for before we came to <hi>Newburne:</hi> we tooke not a groat and after we came the Kings Armie had waſted all, that we found nothing but empty houſes and waſt ground.</item>
               <item>10. Many English put on blew Bonnets called themſelves <hi>Scots,</hi> robbed houſes, and by the way ſome of them being now in priſon for the ſame,</item>
               <item>11. Our victualls ſpent, we demanded victualls and money from the Towne of <hi>New-caſtle</hi> upon ſecurity; who refuſed at firſt to lend us any, onely telling us where the Kings Magdzeens was of Corne, Bread, Cheeſe, and Munition, which was not above 300. ſterling.</item>
               <item>12. They denyed us, that their Bakers and Brewers should provide: us any bread and drinke, shifting us off, by telling us they were fled: our Souldiers for want, gave 12 pence for a loafe of rye Bread of 5. pound weight, and 4. pence a pottle of ſod water, without any ſubſtance in it.</item>
               <item>13. We finding they had reſolution to ſtarve us, told them, if they would not ſell us Corne, it behooved us to take it; and we ſent to the Major deſiring him to ſend C<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtables, with ſome of our Officers, which he did, to ſee what Corne he could find: we agreed with the Merchants for it, and gave them ſecurity; and where the owners were fled, we made Inventoryes of it, in the preſence of the Conſtable, for which we are accountable.</item>
               <item>14. When we had Corne, we could not get it ground, they ſaying their Millers were fled: theſe difficulties being put to, it was the mighty hand of <hi>God</hi> that kept our Army together from pillaging the Countrey.</item>
               <item>15. The chiefe m<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n of <hi>New-caſtle</hi> were gone, and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tranſported
<pb facs="tcp:17380:4"/> their money and goods, nothing almoſt being left but ſome Corne, which we aſſured the <hi>Lord</hi> Almighty provided for us, and not for them.</item>
               <item>16. The Parſon of <hi>Rye</hi> and of <hi>Wickham</hi> firſt rifled their own houſes, and then fled, leaving nothing but a few Play-bookes, and Pamphlets; and one old Cloake, with an old Woman, being the onely living Chriſtian in the Towne; the reſt being fled.</item>
               <item>17. What hath been done at <hi>Durham,</hi> is not ſo fully known to us, but we will informe our ſelves, and make it known to you.</item>
               <item>18. What hath been done in any other perſons houſes is not known to any generall Officer of our Army.</item>
               <item>19. If any diſorderly act hath been committed, none here alows it.</item>
               <item>20. Laſtly, the Ships that came with Rye were brought up the River, we wanting victualls, made a free bargaine with the Merchants; paying them nigh 400. pound of their money, yet have they the victualls in their own poſſeſſions.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
